Guide to the Bernadotte Perrin Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Bernadotte Perrin papers
1876-1914
MS 1018
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.83
(5 boxes)
Student notes on lectures in literature and the classics Perrin attended in Berlin (1876-1878), notes for lectures at Adelbert College and Yale University, corrected proofs for a volume of Plutarch's Lives, and miscellaneous personal papers, largely relating to Perrin's office as writer of the presentations for the honorary degrees at Yale University commencements (1902-1911). Included also is a small amount of correspondence about his publications and five volumes of diaries (1896-1913).
Perrin, Bernadotte, 1847-1920
Biographical / Historical
Bernadotte Perrin, B.A. 1869.
Born September 15, 1847, in Goshen, Conn.
Died August 31, 1920, at Saratoga Springs, N. Y.
Bernadotte Perrin was the son of Rev. Lavalette Perrin (B.A. 1840), a Congregational minister, and Ann Eliza (Comstock) Perrin, and was born in Goshen, Conn., September 15, 1847. His father was at one time associate editor of the Religious Herald of Hartford, and served from 1882 until his death in 1889 as a member of the Yale Corporation. He was the son of Aaron and Lois (Lee) Perrin, and the grandson of Thomas Perrin (or Pering), who came from England to Massachusetts in 1690, removed in 1709 to Lebanon, Conn., and later settled at Hebron, Conn. The family is of French-Huguenot descent, Bernadotte Perrin's given name being that of one of the marshals of Napoleon's army who was later King of Sweden. John Porter, who settled at Windsor, Conn., in 1639, was also an ancestor on the paternal side. Ann Eliza Comstock Perrin's parents were William and Ann (Keeler) Comstock. She traced her descent to William Comstock, who came from Culmstock, Devonshire, England, to Watertown, Mass., in 1635 or 1636, later settled at Wethersfield, Conn., and subsequently moved to New London.
In his Sophomore year at Yale he won two first prizes in English composition, receiving a second prize in the same subject in his Senior year. His appointments were a Latin oration in Junior year and a philosophical oration in Senior year. He was a member of Phi Beta Kappa.
He spent the first year after graduation teaching in the Hartford Public High School, where he had been prepared for college. He attended Yale Divinity School the following year, and was a graduate student in philology at Yale from 1871 to 1873, tutoring in Greek for one term. He was given the degree of Ph.D. in 1873. He was appointed tutor in Greek in September of that year, but left New Haven the next fall to become assistant principal of the high school in Hartford. He resigned this position in May, 1876, and went abroad for study, continuing his work in philology at Tübingen, Leipsic [sic], and Berlin until August 1878, when he again became a tutor at Yale. In 1879 he resumed his former position in Hartford, but resigned in 1881 to accept the professorship of Greek at Western Reserve College (now Adelbert College, Western Reserve University). He spent the summer of 1887 in study and travel abroad, and was in England and Greece from January to September, 1890, devoting part of this time to the study of Greek archaeology. In April, 1893, he was appointed professor of Greek at Yale, and served in that capacity until 1909, when he was made professor emeritus. He was named the first Lampson professor of the Greek language and literature in 1901, the title being changed in 1902 to Lampson professor of Greek literature and history. He served as public orator of the University from 1898 to 1908. Western Reserve University conferred the degree of LL.D. upon him in 1893. He was editor of Caesar's Civil War, school edition (1882); Homer's Odyssey, Books I-IV (with Professor T. D. Seymour; 1897); Twentieth Century Text Books, Classical Section (with John H. Wright of Harvard and Andrew F. West of Princeton; 1901-04); an English translation of six of Plutarch's Greek Lives (1901-1912); and a complete translation of Plutarch's Lives in eleven volumes for the Loeb Classical Library (1914-1920). He had frequently contributed articles on Greek and Roman history and literature to scientific journals. During 1904-05 he lectured at the American School in Athens, of which he was one of the managers. He was a member of Connecticut State Commission of Sculpture, and a Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, and served as president of the American Philological Association in 1897. He was a member of the Church of Christ in Yale College, and had held office as president of the Graduates Club of New Haven.
He died suddenly, of organic heart disease, August 31, 1920, at the home of his brother-in-law, General James W. Lester (B.A. Union 1881), at Saratoga Springs, N. Y. Interment was in Grove Street Cemetery, New Haven.
Professor Perrin was married August 17, 1881, in Lafayette, Ind., to his second cousin, Luella, daughter of James Joel Botts and Margaret Neil (Cason) Perrin, whose death occurred July 25, 1889. He was married a second time November 23, 1892, at Saratoga Springs, to Susan, daughter of Judge Charles Smith Lester, who received the honorary degree of M.A. from Yale in 1854, and Lucy Louisa (Cooke) Lester. She survives him with his two sons by his first marriage, Lee James, '06, and Lester William, '08. Among his Yale relatives were Samuel A. Galpin, '70, John O. Perrin, '79, William H. Perrin, ex-'79, James H. Perrin, '95, Henry L. Galpin, '02, Hervey B. Perrin, '07, John B. Perrin, '09, and Perrin C. Galpin, '10.
(Taken from Yale Obituary Record ).
Scope and Contents
Student notes on lectures in literature and the classics Perrin attended in Berlin (1876-1878), notes for lectures at Adelbert College and Yale University, corrected proofs for a volume of Plutarch's Lives, and miscellaneous personal papers, largely relating to Perrin's office as writer of the presentations for the honorary degrees at Yale University commencements (1902-1911). Included also is a small amount of correspondence about his publications and five volumes of diaries (1896-1913). Also present are photographs from Perrin's trip to Greece in 1890.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Classical education; Greek language -- Study and teaching; Medicine -- United States; Diaries; Educators; Perrin, Bernadotte, 1847-1920; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1869; Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory
  - Student lecture notes, Berlin
    - "Allgemeine und Vergleichende Mythologie", 1876-1879 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Elemente der Vergleich. Sprachwisst...", 1876-1879 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Goethe's Leben und Schriften...", 1876-1879 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Griechische Grammatik", 1876-1879 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Kirchhoff. Griechische Metrix", 1876-1879 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Nicias and Alcibiades", 1876-1879 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Roth. Religionsgeschichte", 1876-1879 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Theokrit", 1876-1879 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous notes on classical subjects, 1876-1879 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Publications
    - "History," reprinted from Greek Literature, New York, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Plutarch's Lives: edited proofs (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - American lectures: Notes for courses given at Adelbert College and Yale University
    - Adelbert College lecture notes: English translations of Homer I., II. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Classical Club lecture notes
      - "Herodotus" (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - "Journal of Visit to Delphi in 1904" (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - "Public Offices of the Poet Sophocles" (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - "Xenophon" (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Yale College lecture notes: history lectures
      - I-IV, VI-VIII, X-XIII, XVI, XVIII-XXII, XXIV-XXXI (Box 3, Folder 17 - 20)
      - Envelopes which contained notes (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Lecture notes: Alexander seminar [from envelope] (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Lecture notes: "Theocritus" (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Notebooks (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Notes on "Plutarch's Pericles and the Athenian Empire" (university extension course no. 3), 1895 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Personal Papers
    - Correspondence, [1873?], 1901-1903, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Perrin, Susan Lester (Mrs. Bernadotte): correspondence, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Perrin's texts for the presentation of honorary degrees. Printed in the Yale Alumni Weekly, 1902, 1904, 1906, 1910, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Clippings relating to Yale commencement, 1908 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Texts (typescript) for presentation of honorary degrees at Yale, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Writings relating to Yale. Yale Alumni Weekly, 1910 December 18, December 2, 1919 July 3 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Diaries, 1896, 1899, 1907, 1908, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 32 - 33)
- Additional material, Circa 1890; Accession 2017-M-0001
  - Athens, Acropolis with Odeon of Herodes Atticus, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Athens street scene, Acropolis in distance, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Athens: home of Heinrich Schliemann ('Iliou melathron'), now the Numismatic Museum., 1890 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Athens, Grand Hotel. [Syntagma Square? Ermou Street?], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cyclopean walls [Mycenae?], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cyclopean walls with arch [Mycenae?], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Cyclopean walls [Mycenae?], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
  - Water, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - View with bay?, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Harbor, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Field and mountains, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
  - Mountains, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Building foundations [ancient walls?], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 21-25)
  - Excavations, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 26-38)
  - Excavations with shed, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
  - Building foundations [ancient walls?], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 41-42)
  - House, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Ancient theater with skene and part of seating area, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Partly excavated structure, modern buildings, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Ancient building parts, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 46-47)
  - Fallen column, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Tourists among ruins, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 49-50)
  - Women washing at ruin (Perrin on far left), 1890 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Two men, rural scene, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Cyclopean walls and foundations, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 53-54)
  - View from Athenian height [Areopagus?], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Athens: long distance view of Acropolis, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Athens: view of city and Mount Lycabettus, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Athens: neo-classical buildling with Hephaistion at the right and Lycabettus behind; unexcavated Agora, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Athens, excavations, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Athens, Hephaistion and Hymettus behind; unexcavated Agora, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Athens, tower of the winds, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Athens, choregic monument, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Athens, Sinaean Academy, completed 1885; now Academy of Athens, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Athens: long distance view of Acropolis, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 64-67)
  - Athens: view of city and Mount Hymettos, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Athens: long distance view of temple of Olympian Zeus, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Athens: temple of Olympian Zeus, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Athens: arch of Hadrian, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Athens: long distance view, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Athens: Acropolis view from behind Parthenon (foundation walls), 1890 (Box 1, Folder 73-74)
  - Field or agora [Athens?], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Bits of columns [Athens?], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Classical ruins [Athens?], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Column; two men; Perrin on right [Athens?], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Building under construction, unexcavated area [Athens?], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 79-80)
  - Ancient cemetery, Athens [Kerameikos?], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 81-84)
  - Excavation/columns [Athens?], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Athens, rooftop view, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Athens, home of Heinrich Schliemann ('Iliou melathron'), now the Numismatic Museum. Panepistimiou Street., 1890 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Athens, [Syntagma square?], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Metropolitan Cathedral of Athens, Metropolitan Square, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Athens: Acropolis with Odeon of Herodes Atticus in front, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 90)